<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2014) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2014) -->

<section anchor="xdr_desc" title="XDR Description of the Flexible File Layout Type">
  <t>
    This document contains the external data representation (XDR)
    <xref target='RFC4506' /> description of the new open
    flags for delegating the file to the client.
    The XDR description is embedded in this
    document in a way that makes it simple for the reader to extract
    into a ready-to-compile form.  The reader can feed this document
    into the following shell script to produce the machine readable
    XDR description of the new flags:
  </t>

  <t>
    &lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;
  </t>

  <figure>
    <artwork>
#!/bin/sh
grep '^ *///' $* | sed 's?^ */// ??' | sed 's?^ *///$??'
    </artwork>
  </figure>

  <t>
    &lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
  </t>

  <t>
    That is, if the above script is stored in a file called "extract.sh", and
    this document is in a file called "spec.txt", then the reader can do:
  </t>

  <figure>
    <artwork>
sh extract.sh &lt; spec.txt &gt; delstid_prot.x
    </artwork>
  </figure>

  <t>
    The effect of the script is to remove leading white space from each
    line, plus a sentinel sequence of "///".  XDR descriptions with the
    sentinel sequence are embedded throughout the document.
  </t>

  <t>
    Note that the XDR code contained in this document depends on types
    from the NFSv4.2 nfs4_prot.x file (generated from <xref target='RFC7863' />).
    This includes both nfs types that end with a 4, such as offset4,
    length4, etc., as well as more generic types such as uint32_t and
    uint64_t.
  </t>

  <t>
    While the XDR can be appeneded to that from <xref target='RFC7863' />,
    the various code snippets belong in their respective areas of the
    that XDR.
  </t>

  <section anchor="code_copyright" title="Code Components Licensing Notice">
    <t>
      Both the XDR description and the scripts used for extracting
      the XDR description
      are Code Components as described in Section 4 of
      <xref target="LEGAL">"Legal Provisions Relating to IETF Documents"</xref>.
      These Code Components are licensed according to the terms of that
      document.
    </t>
  </section>
</section>
