<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt"?>

<rfc
 category="std"
 docName="draft-ietf-nfsv4-delstid-latest"
 ipr="trust200902"
 obsoletes=""
 scripts="Common,Latin"
 sortRefs="true"
 submissionType="IETF"
 symRefs="true"
 tocDepth="3"
 tocInclude="true"
 updates="8881"
 version="3"
 xml:lang="en">

<front>
  <title abbrev="Deleg Stateid">
    Extending the Opening of Files in NFSv4.2
  </title>
  <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-nfsv4-delstid-latest"/>
  <author fullname="Thomas Haynes" initials="T." surname="Haynes">
    <organization abbrev="Hammerspace">Hammerspace</organization>
    <address>
      <email>loghyr@hammerspace.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>
  <author fullname="Trond Myklebust" initials="T." surname="Myklebust">
    <organization abbrev="Hammerspace">Hammerspace</organization>
    <address>
      <email>trondmy@hammerspace.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>
  <date year="2022" month="December" day="10"/>
  <area>Transport</area>
  <workgroup>Network File System Version 4</workgroup>
  <keyword>NFSv4</keyword>
  <abstract>
    <t>
      The Network File System v6 (NFSv4) allows a client to both open
      a file and be granted a delegation of that file.  This provides
      the client the right to cache metadata on the file locally.
      This document presents several refinements to
      <xref target="RFC8881" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/> for
      both the opening and delegating of the file  to the client.
    </t>
  </abstract>

  <note removeInRFC="true">
    <t>
      Discussion of this draft takes place
      on the NFSv4 working group mailing list (nfsv4@ietf.org),
      which is archived at
      <eref target="https://mailarchive.ietf.org/arch/browse/nfsv4/"/>.
      Working Group information can be found at
      <eref target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/wg/nfsv4/about/"/>.
    </t>
  </note>
</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="sec_intro" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="default">
  <name>Introduction</name>
  <t>
    In the Network File System version4 (NFSv4) a client may be granted
    a delegation for a file. This allows the client to act as the
    authority of the file's metadata and data. In this document, we
    introduce some new semantics to both the open and the delegation
    process which allows the client to:
  </t>
  <ul spacing="normal">
    <li>
      detect an offline file, which may be located off premise.
    </li>
    <li>
      determine the extension of OPEN (see Section 18.16 of <xref
      target="RFC8881" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>) flags.
    </li>
    <li>
      during the OPEN procedure, get either the open
      or delegation stateids, but not both.
    </li>
    <li>
      cache both the access and modify times, reducing the
      number of times the client needs to go to the server
      to get that information.
    </li>
    <li>
      for clients using Parallel NFS (pNFS) (see Section 12 of
      <xref target="RFC8881" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>),
      periodically report the attributes of the data files to the
      metadata server.
    </li>
  </ul>

  <t>
    Using the process detailed in <xref target="RFC8178" format="default"
    sectionFormat="of"/>, the revisions in this document become an
    extension of NFSv4.2 <xref target="RFC7862" format="default"
    sectionFormat="of"/>. They are built on top of the external data
    representation (XDR) <xref target="RFC4506" format="default"
    sectionFormat="of"/> generated from <xref target="RFC7863"
    format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>.
  </t>

  <section anchor="sec_defs" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="default">
    <name>Definitions</name>
    <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
      <dt>delegation:</dt>
      <dd>
        A file delegation, which is a recall-able lock that assures the
        holder that inconsistent opens and file changes cannot occur so
        long as the delegation is held.
      </dd>
      <dt>stateid:</dt>
      <dd> 
        A stateid is a 128-bit quantity returned by a server that uniquely
        defines state held by the server for the client. (See Section
        8 of <xref target="RFC8881" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>)
      </dd>
      <dt>weak cache consistency (WCC):</dt>
      <dd>
        In NFSv4, operations are not sent in a compound, hence the client
        would have to perform two round trips to the server in order
        to determine the result of modification to the state of a file
        or directory.  With WCC, the server can return post-operation
        attributes on such operations. As these do not provide a strict
        consistency between the server and client, the client is free
        to ignore the data.  (See Section 2.6 of <xref target="RFC1813"
        format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>)
      </dd>
    </dl>
      </section> <section numbered="true" removeInRFC="false"
      toc="default">
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
    <t>
      The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
      "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
      NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>",
      "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
      "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref
      target="RFC2119" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/> <xref
      target="RFC8174" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/> when,
      and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
    </t>
  </section>
</section>

<section anchor="sec_offline" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="default">
  <name>Offline Files</name>
  <t>
    If a file is offline, then the server locally has the file's
    attributes, but not the file's content. It has to be able to present
    to the client enough information to describe the file, but the content
    is not readily available.  The cost of retrieving the data content is
    expensive, to the extent that the content should only be retrieved
    if it is going to be used.  A graphical file manager (such as OSX's
    Finder) may want to access the beginning of the file to preview it
    for an user who is hovering his pointer over the file name.  If the
    file is retrieved, it will most likely either be immediately thrown
    away or returned.
  </t>
  <t>
    A compound with a GETATTR or READDIR can report the file's attributes
    without bringing the file online.  However, either an OPEN or a
    LAYOUTGET might cause the file server to retrieve the archived
    data contents, bringing the file online.  For non-pNFS systems,
    the OPEN operation requires a filehandle to the data content. For
    pNFS systems, the filehandle retrieved from an OPEN need not cause
    the data content to be retrieved. But when the LAYOUTGET operation
    is processed, a layout type specific mapping will cause the data
    content to be retrieved from offline storage.
  </t>
  <t>
    If an operating system is not aware that the file is offline, it
    might inadvertently open the file to determine what type of file it is
    accessing.  By adding the new attribute FATTR4_OFFLINE, a client can
    predetermine the availability of the file, avoiding the need to open
    it at all. Being offline might also mean that the file is archived
    in the cloud, i.e., there can be an expense in both retrieving the
    file to bring online and in sending the file back to offline status.
  </t>
  <sourcecode name="" type="" markers="true"><![CDATA[
///
/// typedef bool            fattr4_offline;
///
]]>
  </sourcecode>
  <sourcecode name="" type="" markers="true"><![CDATA[
///
/// const FATTR4_OFFLINE            = 83;
///
]]>
  </sourcecode>
</section>

<section anchor="sec_open_args" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="default">
  <name>Determining the Arguments to OPEN</name>
  <t>
    The OPEN (See Section 18.16 of <xref target="RFC8881"
    format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>) procedure returns an
    open stateid to the client to reference the state of the file.
    The client could also request a delegation stateid in the OPEN
    arguements.  The file is said to be "open" to the client as long
    as the count of open and delegated stateids is greater than 0.
    Either type of stateid is suffucient to keep the file open,
    which allows READ (See Section 18.25 of <xref target="RFC8881"
    format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>), WRITE (See Section 18.38
    of <xref target="RFC8881" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>),
    LOCK (See Section 18.12 of <xref target="RFC8881" format="default"
    sectionFormat="of"/>), and LAYOUTGET (see Section 18.50 of <xref
    target="RFC8881" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>) operations
    to proceed. If the client gets both a open and a delegation stateid
    as part of the OPEN, then it has to return them both.  And during
    each operation, the client can send a costly GETATTR (See Section
    18.9 of <xref target="RFC8881" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>).
  </t>
  <t>
    If the client knows that the server supports the
    OPEN4_SHARE_ACCESS_WANT_OPEN_XOR_DELEGATION flag (as determined by an
    earlier GETATTR operation which queried for the FATTR4_OPEN_ARGUMENTS
    attribute), then the client can supply that flag during the OPEN
    and only get either an open or delegation stateid.
  </t>
  <t>
    The client is already prepared to not get a delegation
    stateid even if requested. In order to not send an open
    stateid, the server can indicate that fact with the result
    flag of OPEN4_RESULT_NO_OPEN_STATEID. The open stateid field,
    OPEN4resok.stateid (see Section 18.16.2 of <xref target="RFC8881"
    format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>), should also be set to the
    special all zero stateid.
  </t>

  <section anchor="ssec_open_args_xdr" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="default">
    <name>XDR Modifications to OPEN</name>
    <t>
      <xref target="RFC8178" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>
      (see Section 4.4.2) allows for extending the microversion of the
      NFSv4.x protocol without increasing the microversion.  The client
      can probe the capabilities of the server and based on that result,
      determine if both it and the server support features not specified
      in the main microversion docuument.
    </t>
    <t>
      The XDR extensions presented in this section allow for the OPEN
      procedure to be extended in such a fashion. It models all of
      the parameters via bitmap4 data structures, which allows for
      the addition of a new flag to any of the OPEN arguments (see
      Section 18.16.1 of <xref target="RFC8881" format="default"
      sectionFormat="of"/>). Two new flags are provided:
    </t>
    <ul spacing="normal">
      <li>
        OPEN4_SHARE_ACCESS_WANT_OPEN_XOR_DELEGATION (see <xref target="sec_proxy" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>)
      </li>
      <li>
        OPEN4_SHARE_ACCESS_WANT_DELEG_TIMESTAMPS
      </li>
    </ul>
    <t>
      Subsequent documents can use this framework to introduce
      new functionality to OPEN.
    </t>
    <sourcecode name="" type="" markers="true"><![CDATA[
///
/// struct open_arguments4 {
///   bitmap4  oa_share_access;
///   bitmap4  oa_share_deny;
///   bitmap4  oa_share_access_want;
///   bitmap4  oa_open_claim;
///   bitmap4  oa_create_mode;
/// };
///
 ]]>
    </sourcecode>
    <sourcecode name="" type="" markers="true"><![CDATA[
///
/// enum open_args_share_access4 {
///    OPEN_ARGS_SHARE_ACCESS_READ  = 1,
///    OPEN_ARGS_SHARE_ACCESS_WRITE = 2,
///    OPEN_ARGS_SHARE_ACCESS_BOTH  = 3
/// };
///
 ]]>
    </sourcecode>
    <sourcecode name="" type="" markers="true"><![CDATA[
///
/// enum open_args_share_deny4 {
///    OPEN_ARGS_SHARE_DENY_NONE  = 0,
///    OPEN_ARGS_SHARE_DENY_READ  = 1,
///    OPEN_ARGS_SHARE_DENY_WRITE = 2,
///    OPEN_ARGS_SHARE_DENY_BOTH  = 3
/// };
///
 ]]>
    </sourcecode>
    <sourcecode name="" type="" markers="true"><![CDATA[
///
/// enum open_args_share_access_want4 {
///    OPEN_ARGS_SHARE_ACCESS_WANT_ANY_DELEG           = 3,
///    OPEN_ARGS_SHARE_ACCESS_WANT_NO_DELEG            = 4,
///    OPEN_ARGS_SHARE_ACCESS_WANT_CANCEL              = 5,
///    OPEN_ARGS_SHARE_ACCESS_WANT_SIGNAL_DELEG_WHEN_RESRC_AVAIL
///                                                    = 17,
///    OPEN_ARGS_SHARE_ACCESS_WANT_PUSH_DELEG_WHEN_UNCONTENDED 
///                                                    = 18,
///    OPEN_ARGS_SHARE_ACCESS_WANT_DELEG_TIMESTAMPS    = 20,
///    OPEN_ARGS_SHARE_ACCESS_WANT_OPEN_XOR_DELEGATION = 21
/// };
///
 ]]>
    </sourcecode>
    <sourcecode name="" type="" markers="true"><![CDATA[
///
/// enum open_args_open_claim4 {
///    OPEN_ARGS_OPEN_CLAIM_NULL          = 0,
///    OPEN_ARGS_OPEN_CLAIM_PREVIOUS      = 1,
///    OPEN_ARGS_OPEN_CLAIM_DELEGATE_CUR  = 2,
///    OPEN_ARGS_OPEN_CLAIM_DELEGATE_PREV = 3,
///    OPEN_ARGS_OPEN_CLAIM_FH            = 4,
///    OPEN_ARGS_OPEN_CLAIM_DELEG_CUR_FH  = 5,
///    OPEN_ARGS_OPEN_CLAIM_DELEG_PREV_FH = 6
/// };
///
 ]]>
    </sourcecode>
    <sourcecode name="" type="" markers="true"><![CDATA[
///
/// enum open_args_createmode4 {
///    OPEN_ARGS_CREATEMODE_UNCHECKED4     = 0,
///    OPEN_ARGS_CREATE_MODE_GUARDED       = 1,
///    OPEN_ARGS_CREATEMODE_EXCLUSIVE4     = 2,
///    OPEN_ARGS_CREATE_MODE_EXCLUSIVE4_1  = 3
/// };
///
 ]]>
    </sourcecode>
    <sourcecode name="" type="" markers="true"><![CDATA[
///
/// typedef open_arguments4 fattr4_open_arguments;
///
 ]]>
    </sourcecode>
    <sourcecode name="" type="" markers="true"><![CDATA[
///
/// %/*
/// % * Determine what OPEN4 supports.
/// % */
/// const FATTR4_OPEN_ARGUMENTS     = 86;
///
 ]]>
    </sourcecode>
    <sourcecode name="" type="" markers="true"><![CDATA[
///
/// const OPEN4_SHARE_ACCESS_WANT_OPEN_XOR_DELEGATION = 0x200000;
///
 ]]>
    </sourcecode>
    <sourcecode name="" type="" markers="true"><![CDATA[
///
/// const OPEN4_RESULT_NO_OPEN_STATEID = 0x00000010;
///
 ]]>
    </sourcecode>
  </section>
</section>

<section anchor="sec_proxy" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="default">
  <name>Proxying of Times</name>
  <t>
    When a client is granted a write delegation on a file, it is the
    authority for the file. If the server queries the client as to
    the state of the file via a CB_GETATTR (see Section 20.1 of <xref
    target="RFC8881" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>), then it
    can only determine the size of the file. Likewise, if the client
    holding the delegation wants to know either of the access, modify,
    or change times, it has to send a GETATTR to the server. While it
    is the authority for these values, it has no way to guarantee these
    values after the delegation has been returned. And as such, it can
    not pass these times up to an application expecting posix compliance.
  </t>
  <t>
    With the addition of the new flag:
    OPEN4_SHARE_ACCESS_WANT_DELEG_TIMESTAMPS, the client and server can
    negiotiate that the client will be the authority for these values and
    upon return of the delegation stateid via a DELEGRETURN (see section
    18.6 of <xref target="RFC8881" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>),
    the times will be passed back to the server. If the server is queried
    by another client for either the size or the times, it will need to
    use a CB_GETATTR to query the client which holds the delegation
    (see Section 20.1 of <xref target="RFC8881" format="default"
    sectionFormat="of"/>).
  </t>
  <t>
    If a server informs the client via the FATTR4_OPEN_ARGUMENTS attribute
    that it supports OPEN_ARGS_SHARE_ACCESS_WANT_DELEG_TIMESTAMPS
    and it returns a valid delegation stateid for an OPEN operation
    which sets the OPEN4_SHARE_ACCESS_WANT_DELEG_TIMESTAMPS flag,
    then it MUST be able to query the client via a CB_GETATTR for the
    FATTR4_TIME_DELEG_ACCESS attribute and FATTR4_TIME_DELEG_MODIFY
    attribute. (The change time can be derived from the modify
    time.) Further, when it gets a SETATTR (see Section 18.34 of
    <xref target="RFC8881" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>) in
    the same compound as the DELEGRETURN, then it MUST accept those
    FATTR4_TIME_DELEG_ACCESS attribute and FATTR4_TIME_DELEG_MODIFY
    attribute changes and derive the change time or reject the changes
    with NFS4ERR_DELAY.
  </t>
  <t>
    A key prerequisite of this approach is that the server and client
    are in time synchronization with each other.  Note that while
    the base NFSv4.2 does not require such synchronization, the
    use of RPCSEC_GSS typically makes such a requirement. When the
    client presents either FATTR4_TIME_DELEG_ACCESS or FATTR4_TIME_DELEG_MODIFY
    attributes to the server, the server MUST decide whether the
    times presented are before the old times or past the current time.
    If the time presented is before the original time, then the
    update is ignored. If the time presented is in the future, the
    server can either clamp the new time to the current time, or
    it may return NFS4ERR_DELAY to the client, allowing it to retry.
    Note that if the clock skew is large, this policy will result
    in access to the file being denied until such time that the
    clock skew is exceeded.
  </t>
  <t>
    A change in the access time MUST NOT advance the change time,
    also known as the time_metadata attribute (see Section 5.8.2.42 of
    <xref target="RFC8881" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>), but a
    change in the modify time might advance the change time (and in turn
    the change attribute (See Section 5.8.1.4 of <xref target="RFC8881"
    format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>).  If the modify time is greater
    than the change time and before the current time, then the change time
    is adjusted to the modify time and not the current time (as is most
    likely done on most SETATTR calls that change the metadata). If the
    modify time is in the future, it will be clamped to the current time.
  </t>
  <t>
    Note that each of the possible times, access, modify, and change, are
    compared to the current time. They should all be compared against
    the same time value for the current time. I.e., do not retrieve
    a different value of the current time for each calculation.
  </t>
  <t>
    If the client sets the OPEN4_SHARE_ACCESS_WANT_DELEG_TIMESTAMPS
    flag in an OPEN operation, then it MUST support the FATTR4_TIME_DELEG_ACCESS
    and FATTR4_TIME_DELEG_MODIFY attributes both in the CB_GETATTR
    and SETATTR operations.
  </t>

  <section anchor="ssec_proxy_use" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="default">
    <name>Use case</name>
    <t>
      When a server is a proxy for a NFSv4 server, it is a client
      to the NFSv4 server and during file I/O, it may get a delegation
      on a file. The client of the proxy would be querying the
      proxy for attributes and not the NFSv4 server.  Each GETATTR
      from that client would result in at least one additional
      GETATTR being sent across the wire.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="ssec_proxy_xdr" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="default">
    <name>XDR for Proxying of Times</name>
    <sourcecode name="" type="" markers="true"><![CDATA[
///
/// /*
///  * attributes for the delegation times being
///  * cached and served by the "client"
///  */
/// typedef nfstime4        fattr4_time_deleg_access;
/// typedef nfstime4        fattr4_time_deleg_modify;
///
 ]]>
    </sourcecode>
    <sourcecode name="" type="" markers="true"><![CDATA[
///
/// %/*
/// % * New RECOMMENDED Attribute for
/// % * delegation caching of times
/// % */
/// const FATTR4_TIME_DELEG_ACCESS  = 84;
/// const FATTR4_TIME_DELEG_MODIFY  = 85;
///
 ]]>
    </sourcecode>
    <sourcecode name="" type="" markers="true"><![CDATA[
///
/// const OPEN4_SHARE_ACCESS_WANT_DELEG_TIMESTAMPS = 0x100000;
///
 ]]>
    </sourcecode>
  </section>
</section>

<section anchor="op_LAYOUT_WCC" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="default">
  <name>Operation 77: LAYOUT_WCC - Layout Weak Cache Consistency</name>
  <section toc="exclude" anchor="ss_op_LAYOUT_WCC_A" numbered="true">
    <name>ARGUMENT</name>
    <sourcecode name="" type="" markers="true"><![CDATA[
/// struct LAYOUT_WCC4args {
///         stateid4        lowa_stateid;
///         layouttype4     lowa_type;
///         opaque          lowa_body<>;
/// };
]]></sourcecode>
   </section>
   <section toc="exclude" anchor="ss_op_LAYOUT_WCC_R" numbered="true">
     <name>RESULT</name>
     <sourcecode name="" type="" markers="true"><![CDATA[
/// struct LAYOUT_WCC4res {
///         nfsstat4                lowr_status;
/// };
]]></sourcecode>
   </section>
   <section toc="exclude" anchor="ss_op_LAYOUT_WCC_D" numbered="true">
     <name>DESCRIPTION</name>
     <t>
       When using pNFS (See Section 12 of <xref target="RFC8881"
       format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>), the client is most likely
       to be performing file operations to the storage device and not the
       metadata server. With some layout types (most notably the flexible
       files layout type in <xref target="RFC8435" format="default"
       sectionFormat="of"/>) there is no control protocol between the
       metadata server and the storage device. In order to update the
       metadata state of the file, the metadata server will need to track
       the metadata state of the data file - once the layout is issued,
       it is not able to see the NFSv3 file operations from the client
       to the storage device. Thus the metadata server will be required
       to query the storage device for the data file attributes.
     </t>
     <t>
       For example, with a flexible files layout type, the metadata server
       would issue a NFSv3 GETATTR to the storage device. These queries
       are most likely triggered in response to a NFSv4 GETATTR to the
       metadata server. Not only are these GETATTRs to the storage device
       individually expensive, the storage device can become inundated by
       a storm of such requests. NFSv3 solved a similar issue by having
       the READ and WRITE operations employ a post-operation attribute
       to report the weak cache consistency (WCC) data (See Section 2.6
       of <xref target="RFC1813" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>).
     </t>
     <t>
       Each NFSv3 operation corresponds to one round trip between the
       client and server. So a WRITE followed by a GETATTR would require
       two round trips. In that scenario, the attribute information
       retrieved is considered to be strict server-client consistency for
       a cache consistency protocol. For NFSv4, the WRITE and GETATTR can
       be issued together inside a compound, which only requires one round
       trip between the client and server. And this is also considered
       to be a strict server-client consistency. In essence, the NFSv4
       READ and WRITE operations drop the post-operation attributes,
       allowing the client to decide if it needs that information.
     </t>
     <t>
       With the flexible files layout type, the client can leverage
       the NFSv3 WCC to service the proxying of times (See <xref
       target="sec_proxy" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>).
       But the granularity of this data is limited. With client side
       mirroring (See Section 8 of <xref target="RFC8435" format="default"
       sectionFormat="of"/>), the client has to aggregate the N mirrored
       files in order to send one piece of information instead of N
       pieces of information. Also, the client is limited to sending
       that information only when it returns the delegation.
     </t>
     <t>
       The current filehandle and the lowa_stateid identifies the
       particular layout for the LAYOUT_WCC operation. The lowa_type
       indicates how to unpack the layout type specific payload inside
       the lowa_body field. The lowa_type is defined to be a value from
       the IANA registry for "pNFS Layout Types Registry".
     </t>
     <t>
       The lowa_body will contain the data file attributes. The client
       will be responsible for mapping the NFSv3 post-operation attributes
       to those in a fattr4.  Just as the post-operation attributes may be
       ignored by the client, the server may ignore the attributes inside
       the LAYOUT_WCC.  But the server can also use those attributes to
       avoid querying the storage device for the data file attributes.
       Note that as these attributes are optional and there is nothing
       the client can do if the server ignores one, there is no need to
       return a bitmap4 of which attributes were accepted in the result
       of the LAYOUT_WCC.
     </t>
   </section>

   <section anchor="ss_op_LAYOUT_WCC_errs" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="default">
     <name>Allowed Errors</name>
     <t>
      The LAYOUT_WCC operation can raise the errors in
      <xref target="tbl_op_error_returns" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>. When an error
      is encountered, the metadata server can decide to ignore
      the entire operation or depending on the layout type
      specific payload, it could decide to apply a portion
      of the payload.
     </t>
     <t keepWithNext="true">Valid Error Returns for LAYOUT_WCC</t>
     <table anchor="tbl_op_error_returns" align="center">
       <thead>
         <tr>
           <th align="left">Errors</th>
         </tr>
       </thead>
       <tbody>
         <tr>
           <td align="left">
        NFS4ERR_ADMIN_REVOKED,
        NFS4ERR_BADXDR,
        NFS4ERR_BAD_STATEID,
        NFS4ERR_DEADSESSION,
        NFS4ERR_DELAY,
        NFS4ERR_DELEG_REVOKED,
        NFS4ERR_EXPIRED,
        NFS4ERR_FHEXPIRED,
        NFS4ERR_GRACE,
        NFS4ERR_INVAL,
        NFS4ERR_ISDIR,
        NFS4ERR_MOVED,
        NFS4ERR_NOFILEHANDLE,
        NFS4ERR_NOTSUPP,
        NFS4ERR_NO_GRACE,
        NFS4ERR_OLD_STATEID,
        NFS4ERR_OP_NOT_IN_SESSION,
        NFS4ERR_REP_TOO_BIG,
        NFS4ERR_REP_TOO_BIG_TO_CACHE,
        NFS4ERR_REQ_TOO_BIG,
        NFS4ERR_RETRY_UNCACHED_REP,
        NFS4ERR_SERVERFAULT,
        NFS4ERR_STALE,
        NFS4ERR_TOO_MANY_OPS,
        NFS4ERR_UNKNOWN_LAYOUTTYPE,
        NFS4ERR_WRONG_CRED,
        NFS4ERR_WRONG_TYPE
          </td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
  </section>
  <section anchor="ss_op_LAYOUT_WCC_ff" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="default">
    <name>Flex Files Layout Type</name>
    <sourcecode name="" type="" markers="true"><![CDATA[
/// struct ff_data_server_wcc4 {
///             deviceid4            ffdsw_deviceid;
///             stateid4             ffdsw_stateid;
///             nfs_fh4              ffdsw_fh_vers<>;
///             fattr4               ffdsw_attributes;
/// };
/// 
/// struct ff_mirror_wcc4 {
///             ff_data_server_wcc4  ffmw_data_servers<>;
/// };
/// 
/// struct ff_layout_wcc4 {
///             ff_mirror_wcc4       fflw_mirrors<>;
/// };
]]>
    </sourcecode>
    <t>
      The flex file layout type specific results SHOULD correspond
      to the ff_layout4 data structure as defined in Section 5.1 of
      <xref target="RFC8435" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>.
      There SHOULD be a one-to-one correspondence between:
    </t>
    <ul spacing="normal">
      <li>
        ff_data_server4 -&gt; ff_data_server_wcc4 
      </li>
      <li>
        ff_mirror4 -&gt; ff_mirror_wcc4
      </li>
      <li>
        ff_layout4 -&gt; ff_layout_wcc4
      </li>
    </ul>
    <t>
      Each ff_layout4 has an array of ff_mirror4, which have an array of ff_data_server4.
      Based on the current filehandle and the lowa_stateid, the server can match the
      reported attributes.
    </t>
    <t>
      But the positional correspondence between the elements is not
      sufficient to determine the attributes to update. Consider the
      case where a layout had three mirrors and two of them had updated
      attributes, but the third did not. A client could decide to present
      all three mirrors, with one mirror having an attribute mask with
      no attributes present. Or it could decide to present only the
      two mirrors which had been changed.
    </t>
    <t>
      In either case, the combination of ffdsw_deviceid, ffdsw_stateid, and
      ffdsw_fh_vers will uniquely identify the attributes to be updated.
      All three arguments are required. A layout might have multiple data
      files on the same storage device, in which case the ffdsw_deviceid and
      ffdsw_stateid would match, but the ffdsw_fh_vers would not.
    </t>
    <t>
      The ffdsw_attributes are processed similar to the obj_attributes in
      the SETATTR arguments (See Section 18.34 of <xref target="RFC8881" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>).
    </t>
  </section>
</section>

<section anchor="xdr_desc" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="default">
  <name>Extraction of XDR</name>
  <t>
    This document contains the external data representation (XDR)
    <xref target="RFC4506" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/> description of the new open
    flags for delegating the file to the client.
    The XDR description is embedded in this
    document in a way that makes it simple for the reader to extract
    into a ready-to-compile form.  The reader can feed this document
    into the following shell script to produce the machine readable
    XDR description of the new flags:
  </t>
  <sourcecode name="" type="" markers="true"><![CDATA[
#!/bin/sh
grep '^ *///' $* | sed 's?^ */// ??' | sed 's?^ *///$??'
    ]]>
  </sourcecode>
  <t>
    That is, if the above script is stored in a file called "extract.sh", and
    this document is in a file called "spec.txt", then the reader can do:
  </t>
  <sourcecode name="" type="" markers="true"><![CDATA[
sh extract.sh < spec.txt > delstid_prot.x
    ]]>
  </sourcecode>
  <t>
    The effect of the script is to remove leading white space from each
    line, plus a sentinel sequence of "///".  XDR descriptions with the
    sentinel sequence are embedded throughout the document.
  </t>
  <t>
    Note that the XDR code contained in this document depends on types
    from the NFSv4.2 nfs4_prot.x file (generated from <xref target="RFC7863" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>).
    This includes both nfs types that end with a 4, such as offset4,
    length4, etc., as well as more generic types such as uint32_t and
    uint64_t.
  </t>
  <t>
    While the XDR can be appeneded to that from <xref target="RFC7863" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>,
    the various code snippets belong in their respective areas of the
    that XDR.
  </t>
  <section anchor="code_copyright" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="default">
    <name>Code Components Licensing Notice</name>
    <t>
       Both the XDR description and the scripts used for extracting the
       XDR description are Code Components as described in Section 4 of
       <xref target="LEGAL" format="default" sectionFormat="of">"Legal
       Provisions Relating to IETF Documents"</xref>.  These Code
       Components are licensed according to the terms of that document.
    </t>
  </section>
</section>

<section anchor="sec_security" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="default">
  <name>Security Considerations</name>
  <t>
    There are no new security considerations beyond those in
    <xref target="RFC7862" format="default" sectionFormat="of"/>.
  </t>
</section>

<section anchor="sec_iana" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="default">
  <name>IANA Considerations</name>
  <t>
    IANA should use the current document (RFC-TBD) as the reference for the new entries.
  </t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>

<references>
  <name>References</name>

  <references>
  <name>Normative References</name>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1813.xml"/>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4506.xml"/>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7862.xml"/>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7863.xml"/>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8178.xml"/>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8435.xml"/>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8881.xml"/>
  </references>

  <references>
  <name>Informative References</name>
    <reference anchor="LEGAL" target="http://trustee.ietf.org/docs/IETF-Trust-License-Policy.pdf">
      <front>
        <title abbrev="Legal Provisions">Legal Provisions Relating to IETF Documents</title>
        <author>
          <organization>IETF Trust</organization>
        </author>
        <date month="November" year="2008"/>
      </front>
    </reference>
  </references>
</references>

<section numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>
    Trond Myklebust and David Flynn
    all worked on the prototype at Hammerspace.
      </t>
    </section>

</back>

</rfc>
